<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Instructions for the vse of the beades conteining many matters of meditacion or mentall prayer, vvith diuerse good aduises of ghostly counsayle. VVere vnto is added a figure or forme of the beades portrued in a table. Compiled by Iohn Bucke for the benefit of vnlearned. And dedicated to the honorable good lady, Anne Lady Hungarforde, sister to the duchesse of Ferria.</title>
            <author>Bucke, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112699</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847944</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847944</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13014</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13014)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 238:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Instructions for the vse of the beades conteining many matters of meditacion or mentall prayer, vvith diuerse good aduises of ghostly counsayle. VVere vnto is added a figure or forme of the beades portrued in a table. Compiled by Iohn Bucke for the benefit of vnlearned. And dedicated to the honorable good lady, Anne Lady Hungarforde, sister to the duchesse of Ferria.</title>
                  <author>Bucke, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 87, [2] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[I. Maes],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Lovain :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the yere of our Lorde. 1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes at end a large foldout table.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; as filmed lacking pages 74-75.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rosary --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13014:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13014:1"/>
            <p>INSTRVCTIONS for the vſe of the beades, conteining many matters of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditacion or mentall prayer, vvith diuerſe good aduiſes of ghoſtly counſayle. <hi>VVhere vnto is added a figure or forme of the beades portrued in a Table.</hi> Compiled by Iohn Bucke for the benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of vnlearned. And Dedicated to the honorable good Lady, ANNE LADY Hungarforde, ſiſter to the Ducheſſe of Ferria.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the virgin Mary and Jesus Christ or the Madonna and Child, encircled by rosary beads, with decades divided by two hands, two feet and a heart</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at LOVAIN in the yere of our Lordre. 1589.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:13014:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the Visitation, featuring the virgin Mary, Elizabeth, and the infant John the Baptist; in the background is a city</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13014:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:13014:3"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms of Lady Anne Hungerford, née Dormer</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13014:3"/> TO THE RICHT VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady, ANNE Lady Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garfoorde, his honorable good Maiſtres, Iohn Bucke VViſheth al healthe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or ſo muche as man bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in to this vvorlde hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the no long time to liue Here, he being (as the Wy ſeman ſaithe) lent, not ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to life: And for that vve muſt render an accompt, at the daye of Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t (before that dredefull Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, vvhiche is voyde of partialitie) not onlie of vvoordes and vvoorkes, but of eache moment of time ſpent here, yea euen vnto the thoughtes of our hartes, euerie one in his vocacion and degree: And for my part calling all this to the eyes of my minde: ſeing alſo all my acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hithertho to be verie baſe and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain in his ſight, vvhiche is the true ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of al thoughtes: I began to think hovv I might employe my ſelfe in ſome vvoorke acceptable to ſo bountifull and benigne a patrone, and lorde, as haith
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13014:4"/>beſide my creacion and redempcion, not onlie ſanctified me and preſerued me from my infancie: but alſo brought me out af that darke Egiptiacal England, (the verie ſea of hereſie) and placed me vnder ſo good and graciouſe a ladie, in vvhom I dailie beholde manie examples of true Religion, goldie fear, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, and Chriſtian pietie. Therfore finding nothing more agreable to hys diuine pleaſure, than is the charitable trauail in mouing the deuocio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of others to the effectuall ſeruice of his Diuine Maieſtie by prayer and meditacion: and conſidering hovv great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie a litle direction in prayer may bring to the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vvhoſe vveakeneſſe I vvolde be glad anie vvaye to releue:
<note place="margin">The firſt parte of this boo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke.</note> I haue thought good to put foorth ſuche ſpirituall exerciſes, as I my ſelfe haue priuatlie vſed, vvith great comfort, in ſayieng the Roſaire, Croune, or Pſalter of our bleſſed laidie the virgin Marie, vpon the beades.
<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d part.</note> And I haue alſo ſet doun ſundry meditacions and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racions to be vſed othervvyſe, touching aſvvel the paſſion of our Sauiour and our redemption: as alſo the infinite benefites
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13014:4"/>and Graces moſt plentifullie beſtovved vpon euerie Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: to the ende that in thinking therof a good religiouſe myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de may be more diligent and attentiue to note and marke vvhat is ſayd: more inflamed to deuocion: and more moued vvith compunction and ſorovve for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes committed. And thies meditations a man muy diuide in to ſeuen partes, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the dayes of the vveeke: to the ende that a thankfull hart Dailie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding (as in a glaſſe) the bountifull guiftes of God maye take occaſion to hate ſynne, and to loue God ſo good a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor and patrone. And becauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vvel diſpoſed parſones vvolde fayne vvalke accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the vvil of their lorde and Creator: yet doe they vvander aſtray by vvant of good inſtruction, rather than vpon malice:
<note place="margin">The thrid parte.</note> I haue collected out of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout authors certein leſſons an directio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhevveing, not oulie, good meanes to auoyde ſynne, and to frame the vvhole courſe of lyfe according to hys rule and commaundement, vvhiche ſayeth; <hi>Hoe fac, &amp; viues.</hi> Doe this, and thou ſhault ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue: but alſo profitable ſignes and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, vvhereby one muy perceiue,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13014:5"/>vvhether he ſtandeth in the ſtate of God his grace and fauor,
<note place="margin">The fovverth parte.</note> or no. Laſtlie I haue added ſome rules to knovv from vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce cuell thoughtes do proced eand meanes to auoyde them: vvith a figure or por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trature of the beades, conteining your Lady ſhippes vſuall Meditacion vpon them.</p>
            <p>Thies vvith ſuche lyke being the ſcle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der fruit of my barrain vvyt hauing no better crop to put in to the barne, I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue publiſhed for the benefit of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, vviche can not ſkill of curiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe diſcourſes penned by great clerkes. And I haue preſumed to dedicat this fruit of my poor talent vnto your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip, my honorable, and moſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Maiſtreſſe: by vvhoſe example of Chriſtian lyfe and conuerſacion I haue bene muche edified, and animated, as to other Chriſtian exerciſes, ſo to this vvoork novv here ſet foorthe. VVhiche I hope ſhall fynde better entertein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for that it paſſeth vnder the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of your honorable countenance. And good reaſon I haue ſo to think, for (to omit other places, times, and proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes teſtifyeing your vertues) ſynce your
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13014:5"/>comyng in to thies Countries, you ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue geuen ſuche demonſtracions of true Religion, by the fruits of your good ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe, as for your pittifoll hart, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable compaſſion, vvith the effect of almoiſe and vvoorkes of mercie, I may vvel compare you to Paula, vvhom Seint Ierom ſo highlie commendeth. The tovvne of Louain and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in time of plague famin, vvarre, and hereſie can teſtifie your pietie. The naked then by you clothed, the hungrie then by you fedde, the ſick of daungerouſe diſeaſes than by you vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited, comforted, and releued; the dead then by you buried, the captiues then by you ranſomed, yea the ſimple ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſoules then by your meants recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God and his Churche are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficient teſtimonies and prooſes of your zeale to vertue, and of your perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Catholique Religion: and vvill plead for you before God and man: that as the vvhole courſe of your lyfe hitherto haith bene accompted among the moſt honorable in vertue: ſo vvil your temporall ende be in dede aright famouſe in all good memorie and your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13014:6"/>ſecond lyfe in heauen verie gloriouſe among holie Confeſſors, for (as Seynt Ierom truelie ſayeth) ſeldome or neuer dieth that man an euell death, vvhich vvillinglie exerciſeth the vvoorkes of Charitie. And hys reaſon is, for that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che perſones haue many interceſſors a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong good and vertuouſe poor people: and verie vnlike it is and almoſt impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that none of theyr prayers ſhoulde not be herd.</p>
            <p>And thoughe (good Madame) you haue endured many afflictions and gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous aduerſities: yet haue you no cauſe therfore to be diſcouraged: for they are euident ſignes of the fauor that God bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth tovvard you. It is à peculiar proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God to puniſh them vvhom he loueth. Examples therof vve haue infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite in holy ſcripture and othervvhere. Holy Iob dyd neuer vvillinglie eat mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of bread alone, vvithout company of ſome one or other poor and needy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone: yet vvere his plagues and afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſo terrible, and his diſeaſes ſo lotheſome as vve tede not of any greater. VVho vvas more pittifull to the poor and nedie than olde Tobie, vvhiche buried the dead: fed
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13014:6"/>the hungrie; and ſupplied the vvantes of many: viſited and comforted his felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vves captiues? Yet dyd he bear the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of many heuye croſſes. And vvhen he dyd ſtand in moſt nede of al comfort, he loſt the vſe of his ſight: But vvith thies and ſuche examples of Scripture you are vvell acquainted. I vvill recompt vnto you others. It is vvell knovven hou charitable a hand and hart Seynt Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the great had, the reſtorer of Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Religion in England, to vvhom our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour appeared among others poor beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars, as a ſpecial token that God vvas vvell pleaſed vvith that good mans al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſe dedes, and vvoorkes of charitie: yet vvas he vexed vvith bodilie ſikneſſe continuallie. It is vvritten of a holie vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man called Liduina ſo pittifull tovvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the poor and needie, as vvhen ſhe had not ſufficient of her ovven to geue, ſhe vvolde begge and borovv of others to releue the neceſſitie of the poor, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che encrcaſe oſtentimes folovved her hand, as though ſhe euer gaue vvhere need required, yet dyd her porcion fynde no decreaſe: In ſo muche as one time (if not oftener) thirtie poor perſones vvere
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13014:7"/>vvell releued of the meat that vvas put in one pot, and in the end as muche meat found in the pot as vvas at the fyrſt put in to it. yea ſhe had a purſe vvhere in ſhe vſed to put her almoſe money, vvhiche ſhe called IESVS hys pot, for that it neuer failed: yet vvas this good vvoman euer ſiklic, and often afflicted vvith many moſt greuouſe diſeaſes and aduerſities. And it is vvell knovven hou your Ladieſhipp being at Namure in a time of great famin you releued the hun grie ſoldiors vvith fleſh he and pottage, and hovv God ſo bleſſed your almoiſe, as the meat prouided in tuo pottes for thirtie parſones dyd ſuffice vvell nigh tvvo hundred people. Therfore as you haue Good cauſe vvith that good vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Lidunia to magnifye God, vvhiche gaue you habilitie and good vvil to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the vvoorkes of charitie) and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied your guyſtes in your handes: So haue you good matter of comfort by pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient bearing of your vvordlie afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, expect vvith Liduina the revvard prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for faith ſull and charitable Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: knovveing perfectlie that he vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che geueth but a cup of colde vvater for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13014:7"/>the loue of Chriſt ſhall not leeſe his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarde.</p>
            <p>Thies examples ſhevv you that tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral afflictions caſuallie falling vpon good men, are ſignes and argumentes of Gods fauour. For (as Seynt Gregorie doeth vvell note) there is no greater marke of Gods vvrathe and diſpleaſure, then is a continuall good ſucceſſe in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>althe, vvelthe, and vvordlye proſperitie. Yea ſikneſſe and affliction doeth frame and conforme vs lyke to our Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: vvhom God the Father ſent in to the vvorld not to reap the delica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te pleaſures therof: but to ſuffer great paynes and miſeries. What carefull trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and dredefull perills dyd his bleſſed mother endure, vvhen it vvas knovven that our maiſter Ieſus ſhould be borne? And after he vvas borne a great nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of deadlie enemies dyd dailye ariſe againſt that ſvvete babe and her. VVhat terrible fear and care vvith paynfull la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors dyd ſhe endure traualing ouer hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and dales; vvhen ſhe heard the cries of mothers for their children haled out of their armes and mordered before their eyes: vvhen ſhedyd mete the cruell
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13014:8"/>bouchers that ſought to morder her dear childe by the cruell edict of vvicked He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod, proclaming all male children from troo yeres olde and vnder to be ſlaine? vvhat ſoroufull cares and hard traunlyng dyd that bleſſed virgin endure to hyde and ſaue her oulie ſonne from the cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thoſe ſynfull creatures, vvhom her ſonne came to ſane and kepe from hel and damnacion if they vvolde accept hym? Shal vve then look for priuileige and immunitie from vvordlie afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, vvhen vve ſee that ſpotleſſe lamb the ſonne of God, and the immaculat vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin his mother to haue endured all mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries that the vvorlde could procure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? In verie truthe, afflictions and miſeries ſuſteyned by a faithfull Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian are the bages of our lorde and Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. Therfore vve muſt not grudge to vvear our Maiſters liuereys, and to bear our croſſe and folovv hym: conſidering that in ſo doeing vve haue an aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his entertainement vvith lyfe euerlaſting in his high palace of heauen: VVhereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to he that bought your laidyſhip bring you vvhen it ſhall pleaſe hym. In mean tyme I humblie beſeche you accept this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13014:8"/>myte putin to the box. Interpret of it as I mynde to your honor and to all good Catholiques to vvhoſe vieue it ſhall co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me. I craue onlie the glorie of God he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reby to encreaſe, to vvhom I commend your Ladyſhippe vvith all true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhyppes obedient ſeruant Iohn Bucke.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of the virgin Mary and Jesus Christ or the Madonna and Child, in a room</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="rosary">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13014:9"/>
            <head>CERTAIN MATTERS OF <hi>Meditacion or mentall praeyer to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in reciting the Roſaire, Pſalter, on Croune of our Laidie the most bleſſed vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marie vpon the beades.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is an auncient exerciſe of deuout Chriſtianes in tyme of prayer, and ſpeciallie in the vſe of the beades, to ſet before the eyes oft the Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le ſome conceit or Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion of one or other matter contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the lyfe of our Sauiour, or of the bleſſed virgin Matie. And this conceit vvell imprinted in mynde, vvil kepe it from vvauering in the vain thonghtes, and vvill make it more attentiue and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defull: vverby deuocion is ſoner kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led: vvithout vvhiche prayer yeeldeth ſmall fruit. Therfore vvhen you are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to praey vpon the beades: you may thynke vpon thre ſortes of myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries (vvherof fyue poinctes in every one are Ioyfull, fyue aredolorouſe, and fyue are gloriouſe) in maner folovveing.</p>
            <div type="joyful_mysteries_of_the_rosary">
               <div n="1" type="joyful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:13014:9"/>
                  <head>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of the Annunciation, featuring the virgin Mary in a room with the angel Gabriel in a cloud sending the Holy Spirit (in the form of a bird or dove inside a halo) towards her</figDesc>
                     </figure> Of fyue Ioyfull Mysteries to be thought vpon when you are to pray vpon the beades.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt Ioyfull Myſterie or ſecret is the annunciation of the bleſſed vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary. Ther fore vvhen you take your beades, and haue aduiſedlie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended your ſelfe to God, bleſſing your ſelfe vvith, <hi>In nomine Patris &amp; Filij &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus ſancti. Amen.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciation oft our Lady.</note> Then may you fyrſt ſet before the eyes of your ſoule, the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonciation of our bleſſed ladie: and Imagin in your mynde that you behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the Angel Gabriel preſenting hym ſelfe before that bleſſed virgin vvith hys heauenlie ſalutacion <hi>Aue Maria,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and declaring to her hys meſſage from the Councel of the Thrinitie.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13014:10"/>
                  <p>And vvith that Imaginacion ſtill kept in mynde, ſay the fyrſt <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and ten <hi>Aue Maries</hi> folovveing (vvhiche is the fyrſt part of the beades) attentiuelie, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctlie, and deuoutlie: ther let thies co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s folovveing renne through your mynde avvhile, before you goe any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>Firſt thinck hovv the Angel found her at praier: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and here admoniſh your ſelfe hovv nigh vnto you your good Angel ſtandeth in time of praier: and hovv apt you are then to receiue heauenlie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and good mocions: and that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideracion hereof it is good to pray euer, more or leſſe.</p>
                  <p>Secondlie marke vvith vvhat modeſt ſilence ſhe gaue ear to the meſſaige, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> not vttering any Idle or curiouſe ſpeeche: and ſtudie you to folovve that example.</p>
                  <p>Thirdlie note her zeal to kepe her mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhode and virginitie, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> vovved and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to Gode and ſo thinck to keep your Chriſtian vovve made at your bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</p>
                  <p>Fouerthlie conſider her preſent faith in beleeuing the vvoordes of the Angel, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> paſſing all naturall reaſon that ſhe being
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13014:10"/>a virgin ſhoulde bear a childe: and hete learn faithfullie to beleeue the promiſes of God.</p>
                  <p>Fyftlie beholde her humble obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and reſigned vvil to the diſpoſicion of allmightie God. And vvhen you haue thus occupied your mynde ſome litle ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: then prepare your ſelfe to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde Ioye.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="joyful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of the Visitation, featuring Elizabeth reaching to touch the stomach of the pregnant virgin Mary at the entrance to a house</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>THe ſeconde Ioyfull myſterie is her Viſitacion of her coſſein Seynt Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth.
<note place="margin">The viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of S. Elizabeth</note> Here you may thynke that you ſee the meting of thad bleſſed virgin, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and that holie matrone, vvith the tvvo infantes in their vvombes: vvhat heuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Ioye vvas there. And in this thought ſay the ſeconde <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> folovveing vvith like at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencion and deuocion as before.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:13014:11"/>
                  <p>Then learn a leſſon of great humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and charitie of our lady. And vvhen thou heareſt thy ſelfe commended geue all the thankes to God as ſhe dyd. And if thou art aduaunced to any degree of honor: bear not thy ſelfe more highlie, nor neglect to doe good offices to others vnder thee. Conſider alſo hovv effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall the vvoordes of our Ladie (then haueng conceyved our Sauiour in her vvombe) vvere to cauſe the babe Seynt Iohn to moue, in the vvombe of his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, vvhen the virgin ſaluted her. And therfore ceaſſ not to laude and praiſe her, and to call vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her helpe in thy need. And vvhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt thus thought, begyn the third part of the beades, as foloweth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="joyful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of the Nativity, featuring the Holy family (the virgin Mary, Joseph, and the infant Jesus Christ in a stable with an ox and two figures in the background</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>THe third Ioyefull myſterie is the Natiuitie and byrthe of our Sauiour.
<note place="margin">The Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie of Chriſt.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13014:11"/>Here thynk that thou ſeeſt ſvvete Ieſus nevv borne, vvrapped in poor clothes, layd in a cryb betvvene tvvo beaſtes in an abiect place of a common Inne, for wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of habilitie to hyre a better lodging. And vvith this thought ſay the third <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter noſter,</hi> ad tenne <hi>Aue Maries</hi> folovveing attentiuelie and deuoutlie as before.</p>
                  <p>Then conſider vvith vvhat payn the moſt bleſſed virgin mirrour of humilitie vvent from Nazareth to Bethleem in colde vvinter, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> yeelding obedience to the Emperour: And hovv the ſonne of God vvolde before his byrthe ſhevv obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce vvith humilitie at all ſeaſons: yea to thy inferior if nede requyre or good occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>Secondelie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider in vvhat poor eſtate the lorde of all the vvorlde vvolde be borne and brought in to this vvorlde: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and here learne to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temne al vvorldlie pompe. and vainglorious curioſitie.</p>
                  <p>Thirdlie note here the loue of our Sauiour to mankynde, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and requite hym vvith loue again to the vttermoſt of all thy povvers. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fouerthlie behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de hovv the Angels from heauen prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to poor Shepeheardes the comyng of our Redemer: And here learne
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13014:12"/>to haue euer due regarde to the poor: and imitate thou thoſe poor men vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vvith great zeale ſimplicitie and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence ſought our Sauiour, to yeelde vnto hym all that honor and ſeruice vvhiche vvas requiſit. And after thies thoughtes prepare thy ſelfe to the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerth loye deuoutlie as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="joyful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of the Presentation in the Temple, featuring Simeon, the virgin Mary, Joseph and the infant Jesus Christ, with a male and a female figure</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>THe fouerth Ioyefull myſterie is the Preſentacion of our Redemer in the temple before the Byſhop.
<note place="margin">chriſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde our Lady offering her ſonne in the temple of Ieruſalem: regard hovv olde Simeon the Byſhop (knovveing by reuelacion that babe to be the Sauiour ſo long looked for) tooke hym vp in his armes, and adored hym vvith all Ioye and reuerence, ſayeing: <hi>Now thou doest dimiſſe thy ſeruant o lord, according to thy woord
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13014:12"/>in peace. Becauſe myne eies haue ſeen thy Salua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> And vvith this thought ſay the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerth <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries,</hi> folovveing, deuoutlie as before. And then learne to preſent thy ſelfe oftenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes in the Churche vvithall diligence, reuerence and deuocion, ſpecially at the holy ſacrifice of the Maſſe: that thou mayeſt be parttaker of great myſteries. And thynk hovv Iuſt and faithfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones by deuout prayer, and godlie pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, haue at laſt obteined their holie deſires, as this man dyd. And here alſo marke hovv our Sauiour in his infancie, being but eight dayes olde, ſhed his bloode for thee at his holie Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: and learne for his fake to ſuffer from thy childhode vvhat aduerſitie ſo euer fall vpon thee: And vvith this thought prepare thy ſelfe to the fyſt Ioye deuoutlie as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="joyful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <p>THe fyft Ioye is the finding of our Sauiour in the temple. Here behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de our Lady and auncient Ioſeph vvith great care ſeeking for her ſonne, vvhom ſhe had loſt: and at laſt findeth hym diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting of deep myſteries, vvith great
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13014:13"/>Doctors in the Temple. And vvith that Impreſſion ſaye the fift and laſt <hi>Pater no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries</hi> folovveing, denoutly as before.</p>
                  <p>Then learne here of the virgin and good Ioſeph to ſeeke for Chriſt vvith all care and diligence: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and reſt not till thou finde him.</p>
                  <p>And thinke not to finde him vvith vvorldely affection tovvarde thy kinred, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> nor among the delites of fleſh and blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de: but in the Churche of God, by often hearing the vvoord of God, and freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Sacramentes.</p>
                  <p>Allvvayes prouide to thy vttermoſt povver that thou kepe him in the cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of thy harte: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and leeſe him not after thon haſt founde him. This order thou muſt obſerue in reciting the Roſaire the ſeconde and third time. And vvhen thou haſt thus vvell ended the laſt parte of the beades: then vvith a cherefull couraige and bolde ſpirit thou mayſt ſafelie ſay the concluſion, vvhiche is Credo in Deum, &amp;c. And this muche for the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte Roſarie, or firſt part of the pſalter of our ladie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="sorrowful_mysteries_of_the_rosary">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:13014:13"/>
               <head>Of fiue dolorous Myſteries to be thought vpon when you are to vſe the beades.</head>
               <div n="1" type="sorrowful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of the Agony in the Garden, with Jesus Christ knelt in the Garden of Gethsemane, surrounded by the sleeping Apostles Peter, James, and John</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>VVhen you haue ſayd the Roſarie,
<note place="margin">Chriſt prayeng in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</note> or beades ones ouer, vvith the medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and thoughtes before mencioned: then may you vvith like preparacion and order as before muſe vpon the fiue dolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous myſteries: that is to ſay fiue ſpeciall panges of the ſorovves and paines that our Sauiour endured for our Rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcion.</p>
                  <p>The firſt dolorous myſterie vvas the ſvveating of bloude and vvater vvhiche our lorde and Maiſter ſuffered in the Garden. And here beholde Chriſt in the Garden kneeling vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his knees, holding vp his face and handes to heauen, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13014:14"/>prayeing thriſte to his Father, in this ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. <hi>Father if it be poſſible let this chalice paſſe from me: yet not my will, but thy will be done:</hi> And marke his great agonie vpon the impreſſion and conceit of the great pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vvhiche he vvas to ſuffer vpon the Croſſe for mankynde: and hovv for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie labour of ſorovv he ſvveateth vvater mixed vvith bloude: and beholde vvith all an Angel ſent from heauen ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him. And vvith this Imaginacion ſay the firſt <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries</hi> deuoutlie.</p>
                  <p>Then note firſt hovv in all aduerſities thou muſt flee for ſuccour to God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
                  </p>
                  <p>Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly that it is not enough to praye vvith thy lyppes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> but that all thy ſenſes and invvard povvers muſt be earneſtlie bent to prayer, and that vvith conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance.</p>
                  <p>Thirdlie hovv great nede you haue to pray for auoyding eternall payne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che you haue deſerued for your ſinnes: ſeing the Innocent ſonne of God did flee to prayer for eſchaping or patient enduring a temporall payne to be ſuſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the redempcion and deliuery of others.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:13014:14"/>
                  <p>Fovverthly comfortly continevv in prayer and think that God in the ende vvill hear the, and ſend his holy Angel to releeue thee vvhen neede ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyre. This being doen prepare thy ſelfe as before to the ſecond dolour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="sorrowful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <p>THhe ſecounde dolorous myſterie is the apprehenſion and arraignement of our lorde and maiſter vvith all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of contumelious ſkorne and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te.
<note place="margin">The arrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnement of Chriſt.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And here marke the traitour Iudas betrayeing his maiſter vvith a kyſſe, and the barbarous ſoldiours in armour vvith al violence taking holde of our Sauiour: hailing and dravveing hym by night from Iudge to Iudge, reviling, mocking, and vvith their filthines all beſpitting hym: beholde vvhat ſterne and ſovver countenances they caſt vpon hym: hovv rudely they bynde hym to a piller: hovv vnmarcifully they vvhip and vvound him vvith ſcourges made of hard cordes ſo as no parte of his holy bodie vvas free.</p>
                  <p>And vvith thees thoughtes ſay the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries</hi> deuoutlie: and then conſider that vvhen thou vpon vvillfull malice doeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13014:15"/>any deadly ſinne, thou art become a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor of thy Sauiour, and a part taker and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion vvith Iudas in betrayeing, ſkornyng, vvhipping, and contumelious abuſing thy Redemer.</p>
                  <p>Learne allſo vvith patience to ſuffer all affliction layd vpon the for thy ſinnes: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and refuſe not any payne nor affliction that ſhall be offered to thee for his ſake that ſuffered ſo muche for thee. This benig done prepare thy ſelfe to the third dolour as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="sorrowful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of the Scourging at the Pillar, with Jesus Christ tied to a column while two men whip or beat him with tree branches; four other figure in the background</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>THe thirde dolorous myſterie is the crovvning of our Sauiour vvith a crovvne of Sharpe thornes,
<note place="margin">The crovvne of thorne.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> a horrible torment, and geuen vvith great deſpite: here beholde the moſt ſauaige cruell In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fideles bringing vvith great mockerie a crovvne made of moſt boyſterous ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13014:15"/>thornes, lyke vnto nailes, and beating the ſame violently in to his head: and vvith lotheſome deriſion ſaluting hym as king. A terrible ſight, hable to bruſt the hart of a good Chriſtian to conſider rightly. VVith this Imaginacion and conceyt ſaye the third <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries.</hi> And then note the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent pryde and hypocriſie of all Ievves, heretikes, and infideles againſt the head of the Churche then, and novv againſt his membres. And learne to embrace the true adoring of our Sauiour vvithall humilitie and ſimplicitie, vvithout all pryde and inſolencie. And here note that the propertie of all heretiques is euer vvhith moſt rigeur and malice to aſſault the head principall directors of true religion: vvhiche is a plain demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracion of their diſobedience, thynke therfore hovv thou mayeſt take the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie courſe, and embrace obedience in ſingleneſſe of harte: vvhiche all mightie God more eſtemeth then ſacrifice: and ther vpon conclude thou that Idolatrie is in no degree vvorſe than is diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: And vvith this thought prepare thy mynde to the fovverth dolour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="sorrowful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:13014:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of the Condemnation of Christ, featuring Pontius Pilate surrounded by a group of male figures; including a soldier holding a cross</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>THe fovverth dolorous myſterie vvas the falſe ſentence of Chriſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnacion,
<note place="margin">Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and the heauye burden of his Croſſe. Here beholde the diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling iudge Pilate againſt his conſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, Leading our Sauiour by the Arme, and deliuering that Innocent lambe in to the handes of his foes, to vvreak theire vvicked vvilles vpon him. And vievv the redemer of mankynde his holie bodie vvorne vvith ſtripes and blovves, all blou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye forced to beare a moſt heauie bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of the croſſe, and for verie weakenes falling dovvn vnder it. And vvith this ſorovvfull ſight paſſe ouer deuoutlie the fovverth <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:13014:16"/>And then note that if vve vvill be perfect ſeruantes of Chriſt vve muſt bear our ovvn croſſes: that is, vve muſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientlie ſuffer all paynes, afflictions, and aduerſities vvhiche fall vpon vs for our ſynnes, or for his ſake that endured ſo muche for vs. And here learne to deteſt all falſe Iudgement, and corrupcion of conſcience for any fear or revvarde, leſt thou become an other Pilat by condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Chriſt in his members as he dyd Chriſt in his ovvne perſone. And thus thinking prepare thy minde vvith good deuocion to the fiſt dolour.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="sorrowful_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of the Crucifixion, featuring Jesus Christ nailed to a cross at Golgotha; surrounded by the virgin Mary, John the Apostle, and a kneeling female figure</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>THe fiſt dolorous miſterie vvas the crucifieing of Chriſt.
<note place="margin">The cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifyeing of Chriſt.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde hovv the cruell tormentors do boyſterouſlie pull of his clothes faſt clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to his fleſhe vvhiche procured a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13014:17"/>nevv torment. Marke hovv they ſtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched hym alonge and nayled his handes and feete vvith rough and blunt nailes to the croſſe. Conſider vvhat huge tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he endured in euery member and parte of his bodie, through all his ſenſes ot one inſtant, vvhiles they hoyſed hym vp thus hanging vpon nailes by his han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and fete, vvith all the vveight of his bodie, hauing no other thing to reſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And vvith this terrible ſight ſay the fift and laſt <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</hi> And then dravv together all thy ſenſes and vvith all the povvers of thy mynde conſider hovv thou mayſt fall in to a true mortificacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al thy vices and concupiſcences, and prepare thy ſelfe to dye vvith hym that thou mayſt be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vvoorthie to ariſe vvith hym. This ſight onlie (if thou vievv all circumſtances duelie and througlie) vvil be hable (by the grace of God to pull the avvay from all vvordlie delites, and to ſetle the loue of God rightlie in thy hart. Novv vvhen you haue vvell muſed vpon thees mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, you may conclude vvith a good confidence the Credo. And this muche for the ſecond Roſarie or ſeconde part
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:13014:17"/>of the pſalter of our ladie.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glorious_mysteries_of_the_rosary">
               <head>Of fyue glorious Mysteries to be thought vpon when you are to pray vpon the beades.</head>
               <div n="1" type="glorious_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of the Resurrection, with Jesus Christ emerging from his tomb, surrounded by three soldiers</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <p>VVhen you haue tvvyſe ſayd the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie,
<note place="margin">The reſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rection of Chriſt.</note> or the beades tvvyſe once vvith the meditacions and thoughtes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mencioned: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> then if your laiſure ſerue, It ſhall be good vvith lyke deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion as before to thinke vpon the fiue glorious myſteries vvhiche came after the death of our redemer.</p>
                  <p>The firſt glorious myſterie vvas the reſurrection of Chriſt here may you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the eyes of your minde in vvhat
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:13014:18"/>beautie, brightnes, and gliſtering clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the bodie of our Sauiour ſo before disfigured vvith ſtripes and tormentes is novv riſen again impaſſible, and immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. Beholde hovv he viſiteth firſt is ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovvfull mother to comfort her. Hovv he ſhovveth him ſelfe to Marie Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, and to all his diſciples. And vvith this comfortable ſight repeat the firſt <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutlie. And then vveaghe the glorious victorie of our Sauiour againſt vvhome neither deuell nor hell vvith all their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters vvas hable to preuail further than he hym ſelfe lyſted. Note hovv all the practizes of Ievves againſt the Goſpell are diſapointed and ouerthrovven: Euen ſo ſhall all deuiſes of heretikes vvhen it ſhall pleaſe God. Therfore conſider hovv in all tentacions afflictions, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions and troubles for a Iuſt cauſe, vve muſt not yeeld nor relent to the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: but expect vvith true patience the vvil of God: vvho after a ſtorme ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth fair vvether: after many troubles geueth quietnes, vvith euer laſting reſt. And here may vve conceiue an aſſured hope of our reſurrection in ſoule and bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13014:18"/>and in mean time by continuall prayers and good lyfe to haue many vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and ſightes of our Sauiour in our hartes: as the bleſſed Marie Magdalen and many others had viſible after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="glorious_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <p>THe ſeconde glorious myſterie vvas the Aſcenſion of our Sauiour fortie Dayes after his reſurrection.
<note place="margin">The Aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Here conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hovv our lorde after he had many ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes appeared to his dear mother and to his diſciples, at laſt he called them all to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether on the mount oliuet: and there after a louing farevvell he mounted vp to heauen in all their ſightes vvith great triumphe, accompanied vvith many Sayntes, vvhom before he had deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of Lymbo: and vvith this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſight recite the ſecound <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries.</hi> And pray to God that thou may ſo humble thy ſelfe in this life and ſo kepe thy hart pure and Innocent as thou may aſcend after him to thoſe Ioyes vvhiche God hath prepared for his elect.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="glorious_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:13014:19"/>
                  <p>THe third glorious Myſterie is the coming of the holie Ghoſt.
<note place="margin">The co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the holy Ghooſte.</note> And here thou may vievv the bleſſed mother of God our Redemer, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> together vvith the holie Apoſtles and Diſciples behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the vvonderfull Aſcenſion of our Sauiour: and remaining together in one place, vvith humble prayer and feruent deuocion attending the coming of the holie Ghoſt. And thou may marke hovv the holie Ghoſt to their great coumfort came doune in fyrie tongues in the day of Pentecoſt being the fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth day after the Reſurrection of our Sauiour. And vvith this thought reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te deuoutly the third <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries.</hi> And then note his faithefull performance of his promiſſe, and their firm faith and belefe in the ſame, and vſe thou that example to thy benefit, here all ſo for thy inſtruction and coumfort conſider ſix ſpeciall cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the comyng of the holy Ghoſt: to vvitt, for to reioyçe the penſiue: to reuiue the deade in ſynne: to ſanctifie the vnclean; to confirme his Diſciples in loue: to ſaue the Iuſt: to teache the ignorant. Thees guyftes and graces are
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13014:19"/>preſerued and encreaſed in vs by ſpeciall meanes. vvherof prayer vvith humilitie is one: diligent frequenting the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes vvith hearing diuine ſeruice is an other: continual exercife of the vvoorkes of Charitie is a third for thus it geueth ſtrength againſt all aſſaultes and tentacions of ghoſtlie and bodilie enemyes. Therfore no perill nor perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucion can anoye that perſone vvhiche hath the holy Ghoſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="glorious_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of the virgin Mary and Jesus Christ or the Madonna and Child, encircled by rosary beads, with decades divided by two hands, two feet and a heart</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He fouerth glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rious myſterie is the Aſſumpcion of our Ladie.
<note place="margin">The Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpcion of our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the bleſſed Virgin mother of God and man about the fyfteenth yere after the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of her So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, hauing paſſed her time vvith exerciſes of pietie vvas aſſumed and taken vp to heauen in ſoule and bodye with ineſtimable trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe. And here conceiue the ſight of her Sonne our Sauiour acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied vvith le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions of Angells comyng to conduct her.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13014:20"/>Note hovv the Apoſtles being all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed abrode in the vvorlde exerciſing their functions in ſeuerall farre diſtant places, are miraculouſlie come to gether in a moment to teſtifie her death and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpcion. And vvith thies thoughtes recite the fouerth <hi>Pater noster,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries.</hi> And here conſider hovv our Sauiour can and vvil revvarde thoſe vvhiche ſerue and loue him faithfullie. Marke alſo hovv dear ſhe vvas to hym, and ther vpon hovv auailable her pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are vvith hym.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="glorious_mystery_of_the_rosary">
                  <p>THE fift glorious myſterie is the Crovvning of the bleſſed Virgin Marie,
<note place="margin">The crovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our ladie.</note> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> here beholde hovv that glorious Virgin before aſſumpted in bodie and ſoule vvas in the preſence of all the holy companye in heauen vvith ineſtimable honor and glory by the Holie Trinitie crouned and placed aboue all Angells. And vvith this cogitacion recite the laſt <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> and tenne <hi>Aue Maries.</hi> And then note hovv in heauen ſhe maketh daily interceſſion for the good eſtate of holy Churche: and ys redy to aſſiſt ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che one vvhiche vvith a contrite hart
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13014:20"/>prayeth to her. For the more reuerence and deuocion vve bear tovvardes her, the greater helpe ſhall vve receiue of her ſonne, in all our diſtreſſes. And this vve may be ſure of, that lyuing here ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her example in continence, humilitie, pacience, and mortificacion vve ſhall ariſe at the laſt daye in bodie and ſoule to reſt in heauen for euer. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vvhiche Ioye God of his mercie bring vs, vvhere that bleſſed virgin reſteth in preſence of the Holie Trinitie, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Sonne, and holy Ghooſt. To vvhom be all honor and glorie. Amen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>depiction of the Jesus Christ wearing a crown of thorns and carrying his cross, followed by a group of male and female figures, also carrying crosses</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="meditations">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13014:21"/>
            <head>SEVEN SHORTE MAT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Meditacion touching the benefites vvhiche God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtovved vpon Mankynde.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is requiſite and expedient for euery Chriſtian often to thynke vpon the benefites that God haith geuen to man vvhiche being infinite in nomber and valevv may be reduced to ſeuen principall heades. And thees are the benefites of our Creacion, Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificacion, Vocation, Iuſtificacion, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, Gubernacion, and Glorifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion.</p>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Touching the benefite of Creacion.</head>
               <p>VVe may conſider ſex thinges tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching our Creacion.</p>
               <p>Firſt hovv God hath predeſtinated vs in perpetuall loue before the vvorlde vvas made. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Secondlie hovv he made man moſt lyke to him ſelfe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Thirdlie hovv he hath geuen vs a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a moſt ſeamly conſtitucion and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13014:21"/>proporcion, voyde of many deformities, and made it apt to ſerue him.</p>
               <p>Fovverthly hovv he hath made our ſoule immortall, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and adorned it vvith many qualities moſt precious.</p>
               <p>Fiftlie that he haith appointed for ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che one of vs a Good Angell to guyde and keep vs. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Sixtlie that he hath geuen vs a prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue to be borne of Chriſtian paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, not of infideles nor heretiques. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> And of thies matters you may thynke vpon, vvith great profit, geuing God due than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes for the ſame euerie monday at mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, noone, or night, as your laiſure vvill permit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Touching the benefit of Gratificacion.</head>
               <p>VVe may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider ſix thinges touching Gratificacion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt hovv God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſent among vs his vvelbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued Sonne, to be our redemer and our exemplar to folovv.</p>
               <p>Secondlie hovv he hath geuen vs the holie Ghooſt in token of adopcion as a priuileige of loue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and a pledge of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſacion, communicating vnto vs his inſpiracions, guyftes, and fruites.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13014:22"/>
               <p>Thirdlie hovv he haith beſtovved on vs his holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes in his holy Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che there to haue a refuge and place of ſuccour (as in the Arke of Noe) from the fludde of ſynne and iniquities.</p>
               <p>Fouerthly hovv by baptiſme he haith purged vs of Originall ſinne; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and as it vvere haith reſtored to vs the veſture and Innocencie of originall Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>Fiftlie hovv he haith fortified vs vvith the Sacrament of Confirmacion; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> vvher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he haith armed vs agaynſt many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences.</p>
               <p>Sixtly hovv he haith made vs Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> according to the name of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt: making vs ther by the ſonnes of God by adopcion, and coheyres of his kingedome. And of thies matters you may thynk of euery tevveſtaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Touching the benefite of vocacion.</head>
               <p>VVhe may conſider ſix thinges tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching vocacion. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt vvith vvhat great patience he haith borne vvith vs falling ſo often from him after ſo many and ſo great benefites. Hovv he haith long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected our returne to him: forbearing to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne vs eternallie: not permitting vs
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13014:22"/>to dye in our vvickedneſſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Secondlie hovv many vvayes he haith ſought to recall vs: ſometime by invvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de inſpiracions: ſometime by admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of other men: ſometime by exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacions of holy ſcriptures: yea oft<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>etimes by large and bountifull guyftes of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, fortune, and grace: ſometime by eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſhovves of eternall Ioyes.</p>
               <p>Thyrdlie hovv he haith broken our hard hartes: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> hovv he haith geuen vs a good vvil to vertue: and remoued all thoſe Impedimentes that myght vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dravve vs from him.</p>
               <p>Fouerthly hovv fatherlie he haith en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terteined vs vvhen vve haue returned to him: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> hovv he imbraſed vs as the father dyd his prodigall ſonne and put vpon vs the ſtole of Innocencie vvhiche by ſinne vve had loſte.</p>
               <p>Fiftly that he hath moued vs to harty repentance, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and therby haith called vs from the company of ſinnefull people, as he called Loth from Sodom: Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham from the Chaldees, and Nohe from the fludde.</p>
               <p>Sixtlie hovv he hath put vs in a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med place, in his holy Churche: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> vvhere
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:13014:23"/>vve may liue religiouſlie doeing pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for our ſinnes. And hath ſet vs in a ſtate to preuent the malice of ſinne, and hath remitted our ſinnes by the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of pennance. Of thies matters you may think euery vvedenſdaye.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Touching the benefite of Iustificacion.</head>
               <p>In conſidering this benefit of Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacion: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> vve are firſt to thank God for that he hath chaunged our vvill: made vs apt to doe pennance; and to doe that ſvveetly, vvhiche before vvas bitter to vs: and hath geuen vs the ſpeciall guyft of continence.</p>
               <p>Secondlie for that he hath geuen vs conſtant perſeuerance in faith fear and loue: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> vvhen many vvhiche dyd vvel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne haue failed in the ende to their damnacion.</p>
               <p>Thirdly for that he hath geuen vs the euangelicall vertue hope, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and grace to ſaue vs from leauing our good purpoſe: by inſpiring into vs many internall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolacions, vvith a minde to deteſt ſinne, and a deſire of the Ioyes to come.</p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fouerthly for that he hath to our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13014:23"/>left vnto vs the bleſſed Sacrament of the bodie and bloude of our Sauiour, as a <hi>viaticum</hi> or neceſſarie prouiſion for our releefe in our iourney.</p>
               <p>Fiftely for that he hath left vs the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures vvherein, as in a Glaſſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> vve may beholde our defectes, and our alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racions: and inflame our hartes vvith dailie deſyre to be purged and iuſtified.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> for that he hath endued vs with the ornamentes of many vertues, therby to couer the filthynes of our ſinnes. And hath left vs many examples of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly martyrs, confeſſors, virgins and other Seyntes to kepe vs by imitating them from fallyng and faynting in our good purpoſe. And thies matters you may vſe euery Thureſday.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Touching the benefite of Dotacion.</head>
               <p>Here vve may firſt thynke of the guyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of nature, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> fortune and Grace vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he moſt largelie and beningnely haith beſtovved vpon vs: as felyng, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſeyng, vnderſtandyng, vvill and memorie: Riches, honor, and vvorldly vvealth: ſtrength, beautie, and health: faith, hope, and charitie.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:13014:24"/>
               <p>Secoundly hovv that among many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prefermentes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> he hayth reduced vs home to the Shepefolde vvhen vve wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and ſtrayed abroade: and haith in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed vs vvhen vve vvere ignorant: and lyfted vs vp vvhen vve vvere fallen in ſinnefullneſſe of lyfe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly how he haith illuminated our vnderſtanding vvith knovvleige of his ſecretes: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and haith vvrought in vs many godly mocions to deuout purpoſes.</p>
               <p>Fovverthly hovv he haith inflamed our deſires, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and haith delited our vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>template, thynke, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate of heuenly thynges: and therby haith geuen vs a taſte and entrance to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting lyfe.</p>
               <p>Fiftlye hovv he haith preſerued vs from the vvounde of ſinne, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> putting avvay the occaſiones: and haith geuen vs the grace to preuent or reſiſt ſinne: and ſo healed our affections, as vve may the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer in exerciſes of pietie.</p>
               <p>Sixtly hovv he haith ſo delyuered vs from the daunger of tentacion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> as he haith raiſed vs when vve vvere fallen: and endevved vs vvith greater ſtrengthe to reſiſt than vve had before. And of thies
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13014:24"/>matters you may conſider euery fryday, and yeeld to him al devv thankes for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Touching the benefite of gubernacion.</head>
               <p>Here vve are to thinke hovv he haith preſerued vs euer bodily and ghooſtlye in good eſtate, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> vvith encreaſe of ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the and couraige to execute all good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions.</p>
               <p>Secoundly hovv from our Cradels to this moment he haith preſerued vs from many enemies, diſeaſes, daungers, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences.</p>
               <p>Thirdly hovv he haith hitherto fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed vs vvith all neceſſaires of meat, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> drinke, clothe, loging and other thinges.</p>
               <p>Fovverthly hovv he haith for vs or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined courſe and ſucceſſion of times, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> as day and night vvinter and ſommer, ſpring tyme and harueſt, vvith diuerſitie of ſeaſons and varieties of thinges for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyding of vvearines, and tedious lothe ſomenes.</p>
               <p>Fiftlie hovv he haith directed vs in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie and aduerſitie: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> in ſiknes and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alth: and in the vvhole courſe of our lyfe.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13014:25"/>Bearing vvith our infirmities, remitting our enormityes: encreaſing our merites: and of thies matters you may think euery Saterday and geue God thankes for theſe benefites.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Touching the benefite of glorificacion.</head>
               <p>Here vve are to conſider and to thank God for many thinges of diuerſe degrees and qualities touching our glorificacion, vvhiche he hath ordeined for vs, if vve lyve and dye in his grace and fauour: and of thies, ſome are aboue vs, ſome nigh vs, ſome vvithin vs, others vvithout vs, ſome vnder vs, and many all about vs.</p>
               <p>Touching the firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> vve are to thank hym for the Ioyes of heauen, vvhiche of his ſingular bountie and magnifence he hath promiſed vs: as the fruicion of his Diuinitie: the viſion and ſight of our redemer, vvith his bleſſed mother. And here conſider vvhat vnſpeakable Ioye it ſhalbe to beholde the bleſſed Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie glorifyed in heauen: vvith all the orders of Angels.</p>
               <p>And touching the ſecond, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> conſider hovv vve ſhall there enioye the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paines
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13014:25"/>of all patriarches, prophetes, martyres, confeſſors, virgines, and other Seyntes and deuout Chriſtianes vvhiche haue bene ſyns the begynning of the vvorlde, and for their integritie of life are novv moſt cleare and bright, and in nomber infinite.</p>
               <p>Touching the third poynt vve haue to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider and to thanke. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> God for the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacion of our ſoules and bodies, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed vvith immortalitie, bright ſhining a boue the clearenes of the ſonne, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for vs if vve lyue in this vvorlde ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our profeſſion.</p>
               <p>As for the fovverth vve are to looke for a place moſt pleaſant to beholde, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> moſt delectable to all our ſenſes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding: and in that reſpect to thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke our ſelues at all times moſt bounde to thank, laude, and glorifie our redemer.</p>
               <p>Touching the fift vve haue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider hovv by diuine grace vve ſhal eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chape our terrible and cruell enemyes that are in the pyt of hell: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> a ſingular motiue to induce vs euer to geue God thankes.</p>
               <p>As to the ſixt degree, to vvit, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> of thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that are on euery ſyde about vs
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:13014:26"/>vve haue to thynke vpon many guyftes and graces that God haith beſtovved v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, innumerable, ineſtimable, vnme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable: And alſo to conſider the infinit euels and miſeries from vvhiche God hath preſerued vs: and hovv vve ſhalbe in ſafetie and ſecuritie deliuered from all that vve nede to fear: enioyeng all thinges vve can deſyre.</p>
               <p>Thus muche touching the benefites vvhiche God haith geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Theiſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges euerie good Chriſtian is bovvnd to thynk vpon daily eyther in all or in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and to endeuour him felfe to be than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kefull. For ingratitude is a great part of Iniuſtice. And among all Chriſtian exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, none is more eaſie, (if vve be vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling) none more nedefull, (if vve regard our duetie) none more profitable (if vve look for revvarde) than is often to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate conſider and thynke of the great and maniſolde benefites vvhiche vve ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue receiued of God: for vvhat may be the cauſe vvhy vve fele ſo great decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and vvant of guyftes and graces vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in time paſt vve enioyed, but only our ingratitude? vvhat other better mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can vve fynde to preſerue our ſelues in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13014:26"/>the fauour of God than by often callyng to mynde and memorie the benefites of God tovvardes vs? This kynde of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditacion is as it vvere a corde to hall and dravv vs to God. Nothing more kynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in our hartes the loue of God (ſayeth ſeynt Auguſtin) than often to vveagh and conſider the benignitie of God to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvarde vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Certein circumſtances touching the paſsion of our Sauiour verie profitable to be often thought vpon to moue contricion and amendement of life.</head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the Crucifixion, featuring Jesus Christ nailed to a cross at Golgotha; surrounded by the virgin Mary, John the Apostle, and a kneeling female figure</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>A Man may vvith great commoditie meditate vpon the paſſion of Ieſus Chriſt our Redemer, in admiring his vvonderfull great charitie, humilitie, and patience. vvhiche appeareth by fovver
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13014:27"/>circumſtances. To vvitt, if a man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider vvho he vvas that ſuffered: vvhat he ſuffered: by vvhom he ſuffered: and for vvhom he ſuffered. Vnderſtand then that he vvhiche ſuffered vvas the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of the vvorlde: Lord commaunder and gouernour of all creatures: Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe it ſelfe: the ſonne of God, and God him ſelfe: he ſuffred baniſhement, hungar, thurſt, colde, tentacions, I kor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, contumelies, bondes, beatinges, vvoundes, and villanouſe crueltie, vvith all deſpite that the deuill by man could execute againſt hym. Therfore in vvei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghing of thies tvvo circumſtances <hi>(who and what)</hi> you may eaſilie conceiue, that the parſone ſo perſecuted vvas ſo great, and the indignities vvhiche he endured vvere ſo monſtruous, as you may vvell ſay and thinke, that the Iudge of the vvorlde vvas him ſelfe arraigned and Iudged: Iuſtice it ſelfe vvas condemned: Innocencie it ſelfe vvas accuſed, bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and defamed: Glorie it ſelfe vvas vvith all opprobrie ſpit at: God him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe openlie to his face blaſphemed: light extinguiſhed: and life vvas ſlaine: The Segnior, lorde, and maiſter of heauen
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13014:27"/>and earthe vvas put to death: to the moſt cruell, moſt ſhamefull and moſt reprochefull death of the Croſſe: and ſo horriblie abuſed, as the verie elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes repined againſt the fact: The ſonne loft his light, and the earthe trembled vvhith the horror therof. Here behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de the meruelous pacience of the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer: vvhiche in a moment, vvith a thought, might haue conſumed all tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe vvreches, and throvvne them in to the fyre of hell. And at vvhoſe handes did he beare all thies indignities? of vvhom did he ſuffer thies contumclious cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties? for ſuthe of his ovvn creatures vvhom he had made of naught: of his ovvn ſeruantes and vaſſailes, vvho had there being of him, and euerie other good thing elſe. VVhom he had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen and picked out from the reſt of the vvorlde for his ovvn peculiar people: vvhom he had higlie aduaunced in the ſight of the vvorlde.</p>
               <p>But for vvhome dyd he ſuffer thies afflictions? not for any fault that he him ſelfe committed: but euen for them that thus traiterouſlie abuſed him: for them he ſuffered vvhiche contemne
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13014:28"/>him and all goodneſſe. he ſuffered theſe paynes to deliuer his enemies from pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne: to pay their ranſome and to redeme them from the daunger of ſinne, from damnacion, deathe and hell, if they vvol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de repent in time and reconcile them ſelues to him. If you deeplie thinke of thies fovver circumſtances, you ſhall finde matter enough to vvonder at the marcie, clemencie, patience, longani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie and charitie of our Redemer: and Iuſt cauſe ſhal you ſee to accuſe, blame, and condemne your ſelues of ingratitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, to fall in to repentance, grefe, and ſorow for your ſinnes: to ſeke to reforme your ſelues, and to flee to him for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour: to ſtudie vvith all loue and dutie to requite him vvith loue, vvhiche for your ſakes endured all thies miſeries.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Of thre ſpeciall ſortes of meditacion, ſome what hard to exerciſe, but paſsing profitable.</head>
               <p>THere is one kinde of meditacion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> vvhiche if you can reache vnto, you ſhall need neither booke nor beade to direct you the vvay to life euerlaſting.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13014:28"/>This kynde of meditacion is no more but to imitate and folow our Sauiour his life and conuerſacion, as a moſt perfect patern and exemplar of all integritie in vvoorde, deed, and thought: to be cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, obedient, humble, patient, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, and marcifull as he vvas: to renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce proprietie and poſſeſſion of Riches (at leaſt in deſire) as hedyd: to be poor and needy (at leaſt in mynde and vvill) as he vvas: To profeſſe and exerciſe all chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or continence as he dyd: to reiect all delicate fare, ſvvete odours, ſoft beddes, and daintines, as he dyd: to employ all your trauaill, induſtrie, and povvers in profiting others as he dyd for you all: yea patientlie to ſuſtein affliction, contempt, and all perſecucion, euen death it ſelfe, and death vvithcruell torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for truthe ſake, and for defence of iuſtice, if oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion be offered, as he did for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie of mankynd from damnacion: and for teſtimonie of true Religion. This is the moſt perfect kynde of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion, conſideracion, and thinking of God that can be vſed.</p>
               <p>There is an other kinde of meditacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of great perfection, and commoditie,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13014:29"/>and is a good mean to help vs to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor. And that is a continuall compaſſion and ſuffering vvith our Sauiour vvhiche ſuffered ſo muche for vs: As vvhen his afflictions and tormentes haue ſuche an Impreſſion in our myndes and thoughtes as vvhe haue ſome ſenſible feeling therof in mynde and bodie or at leaſt in mynde and affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Suche an Impreſſion had the bleſſed virgin, vvho as it vvere felt the ſtinges of the vvhippes, the prickes of the thornes, the ſtampes of the nailes, the tormentes of the croſſe: and the vexacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of all his paſſion, vvho ſo euer can reache to this contemplacion, is in an highe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of perfection.</p>
               <p>There is yet a third ſpeciall kynde of meditacion verie gainfull and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> not ſo hard as the other too. And that is (if thou canneſt not attayn to the one or thother of the too) yet to ſet dovvn a free reſignacion, and perfect reſolucion of thy vvill hart and mynde (vvith all thy povvers as farre as thou canneſt) to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv the vertues of our Sauiour: and a deſire to ſuffer vvith him and ſo to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13014:29"/>thy vvil and mynde in to Ieſus Chriſt crucified, as he be neuer or ſeldome out of thy ſight, euen as he vvas hanging vpon nailes on the croſſe for vs ſinfull creatures, according to the ſayeing of him vvhiche ſayd he felt nothing in him ſelfe but Chriſt crucified, mocked and blaſphemed. This continuall thinking of Chriſt vvith a deſire to folovv his ſtep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes vvil vvoorke great effectes in ſuche as vſe this.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>An other ſort of meditating of the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our Sauiour by way of reioyeſinge.</head>
               <p>AS vve vſe moſt commonlie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the paſſion of our rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer vvith compaſſion, to break our har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes vvith contricion and true repentan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce: ſo may vve to the ſame effect thinke there of vvith great Ioye and comfort: And that for thre reſpectes: to vvitt, for the redempcion of mankynde: for the reparacion of the dekaye of Angels: and for the aduauncement of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God. VVho by the death,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13014:30"/>paſſion and reſurrection of his ſonne our Sauiour hath not only ſet vs free from the bondage of Sathan: but hath alſo vnited angels and mankynde in that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlie ſocietie. And thus to his paſſing great honor and glorie hath geuen a moſt expreſſe demonſtracion of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercie, clemencie, and loue tovvar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des vs. A matter of great loye conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and comfort to vs. For eache man accompteth it a great cauſe of Ioye to be in great fauour of his temporall prince. Muche more glad and Ioyfull may vve be that the king of heauen and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the vvorlde doeth ſo tenderlie lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue vs as he did voncheſafe to offer vp him ſelfe in ſacrifice to his father for vs: and vvith his precious bloudde to rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vs. Thus vve may thinke, meditate, and conſider of his moſt bitter paſſion, vvith great comfort and ioye. For if vve deeplie and duelie vveighe the matter: our hartes ſhall melt vvith feruor of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to reuerence, ſerue, and loue him vvhiche ſo dearlie haith bought vs. Yea vve ſhal be ſo caried avvay vvith ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re affection tovvardes him; as vve ſhall cleare forget our olde man: and reſt on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13014:30"/>ſo reſolued in Chriſt crucified, as vve ſhall delite in nothing but in him, and in doeing that vvhich is his vvil and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to be doen: vvhere vpon many good effectes vvil folovve. It vvill breed in vs a ſpeciall lotheſomenes, hatred, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine againſt all filthie vvoorkes, vvoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and thoughtes: It vvill chaſe avvay the coldenes of ſpirit, the tedious ſlothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of mynde: and inflame our deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion: and ſetle in vs a perfect reſolucion of minde and vvill to ſerue God, loue God, and honor God vvith all integritie: and bring vs to the highe tovvre of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect contemplacion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Of ſix matters of meditacion to ſaue vs from relapſe or falling again in to ſinne after we be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to God.</head>
               <p>EMong many good thoughtes and conſideracions, that help to preuent ſinne, good men of experience in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall exerciſes haue noted ſix ſpeciall meanes. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is often to meditate and thinke of death: that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more certain than that vve muſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13014:31"/>ones die: that nothing is more vncertein than the hovvre of deathe. Therfore ſaith holie Scripture: <hi>Remembre thy ende and thou ſhalt not ſinne for euer.</hi> VVherby is ment that the memorie of deathe (if it be often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed) vvil vvorke in man ſuche com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction as he ſhall not dye vvithout perfect repentance: And ſo by a conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence obtein ſuche remiſſion as his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ſhall not burden him for euer. And Seint Auguſtin ſayeth that nothing more vvithdravveth a man from ſinne, than often to remember that he muſt dye. And Seynt Baſil the great being aſked vvhat is philoſophie, anſvvered that the definition of the principal phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie is nothing elſe but a medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion and continuall thinking of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the.</p>
               <p>An other remedie is to think often of Chriſt his paſſion, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as many good men haue founde by experience. Therfore ſayeth Seynt Auguſtin let man be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſvvell vvith pride, ſithe Chriſt his creator and redemer vvas ſo humble as to ſuffer death for him.</p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:13014:31"/>
               <p>The third helpe is the remembrance of ſinnes comitted, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and by God forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Therfore vvhen thou art temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſinne conſider vvith thy ſelfe vve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou haſt bene culpable of that ſinne before or no. If thou haſt not bene ſo, then impute it to the grace of God that thou vvaſt ſo preſerued. But if thou haſt offended therein before, and by the ſacrament of pennance God hath forgeuen thee: then thinke that he hath doen more for thee, than if he had made the lorde of the vvhole vvorlde. For Seynt Auguſtin ſayeth that it is a matter of greater importance to Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye a ſinner, than to creat heauen and earth of nevv.</p>
               <p>The fovverth preſeruature is often to thynke and meditate of the laſt Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement or day of dome. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> VVher vpon Seynt Ierom vvriteth thus: vvhether I ſleep or vvake, or be other vvayes oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied, that voice and crie euer ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in my eare: <hi>Ariſe you that are dead, and come to Iudgement.</hi> And good reaſon he had to be carefull the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rein. For (as Seynt Barnard ſayeth:)
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:13014:32"/>God at that day will call for acompt and reckeninge of euerie time and moment that vve haue ſpent in earthe.</p>
               <p>The fift mean is to thinke and medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of the paynes of hell, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> vvhiche are ſo great and intollerable, as one ſpetk of that fyre (as a good man ſayed) Doeth more greue a ſinner, than the greuous panges of childebyrth can torment a vvoman if ſhe ſhould trauail a thouſand yeres before her deliuerie. Yea (ſayeth ſeynt Ambroſe) if all men borne from Adam vvere liuing and preachers, and ſhould ſtriue to ſhovv their beſt elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to deſcribe expreſſely but one of the leaſt paynes of hell, yet could they not doe yt. The reaſon is, for that it is infinite, and excedeth the capacitie of mannes vvit to comprehend: euen as on the contrarie parte, faith can not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, hope can not reache vnto, nor cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie comprehend vvhat and hovv many thinges God hath prepared for them that loue him.</p>
               <p>The ſixt remedie is to conſider and meditate of the Ioyes of heauen: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> VVhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, for taking litle paynes in this lyfe vve are ſure of ſuche felicitye as can not be
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:13014:32"/>expreſſed by tongue, nor comprehended in the vnderſtanding of man. A certein paynim being of great authoritie vnder one of the perſecutors of Chriſtians, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing hovv vvilling Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men vve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re to endure all tormentes, yea and death alſo for Chriſt his ſake, demaunded of a preſoner expecting death, vvhat great revvarde he looked for to recompence his patience. It vvas anſvvered thus: <hi>ſuche rewarde is looked for as no tonge can tell, nor ear hath heard, nor the hart of man can mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi> Then ſayd the pagan (if it be ſo) I vvil be of your Religion. So he became à Chriſtian, and aftervvard a martire. If a paynim vvas ſo touched vvith only ones hearing of thoſe Ioyes: hovv ought vve to be moued that haue heard ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny teſtimonies therof by ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nout martyres and confeſſors?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="meditation">
               <head>Of the miſeries and Inconueniences that man doeth fall into by relapſe and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning again after reconciliacion to God.</head>
               <p>VVhen a man hath rightlie profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſt in the Catholique Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che and aftervvarde falleth again: he is
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:13014:33"/>in vvorſe ſtate than euer he vvas, and brought in to extreme miſerie.</p>
               <p>For firſt he hath loſt the fruit of his former pennance, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and of all confeſſion, contricion, and ſatisfaction for his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes paſt and forgeuen. For (as the prophet ſayeth) if the Iuſt man diuert from his Iuſtice, all the good vvoorkes that he hath doen ſhal be put out of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie.</p>
               <p>Secondly he is reſembled to a dogge that ſvvalovveth his ovvn filthy vomit: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In that he reſumeth his olde ſinnes, that vvere ones caſte ovvt by the ſacrament of pennance.</p>
               <p>Thirdly he falleth again in to the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of his greateſt enemie againſt vvho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe vvill he vvas delyuered: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and geueth to him greater povver ouer him ſelfe, than he had before. For (as Seynt Auguſtin ſayeth) he vvhiche heapeth ſinne vpon ſinne, maketh a roope to bynde him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe vvithall.</p>
               <p>Fovverthly he is made more impote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and leſſe hable to ariſe agayn. For as a ſkarre in a mans bodie is harder to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red after the place be vvounded agayn: ſo is a ſinner after he returne to his olde
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:13014:33"/>folie. Therfore our Sauiour ſayd to the man vvhome he had healed:
<note place="margin">Iohn 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Beholde thou art made whole: ſinne no more, lest ſome worſe thing chaunce to thee.</hi> And of this miſchefe he vvarneth vs in an other place, vvhere he ſhevveth, that the vnclean ſpirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth in to the houſe vvhence he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, and bringeth ſeuen other ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites vvorſe than him ſelfe, and dvvelleth there. <hi>And the last of that man be made wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe than the first.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftlie he is accompted a derider and mocker of God: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> and abuſeth the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and clemencie of his redemer.</p>
               <p>Sixtlie (as muche as in him lyeth) he cauſeth the Angels and bleſſed Seyntes in heauen to be penſiue and ſade, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> for as of their charitie they reioyſe at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of a Synner: ſo it may vvell be thought that they are forie for the fall of the Iuſt.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly his ſoule is compared to a drie and wethered braunche cut of from the tree vvhiche receiueth no moyſture nor noriſhement of the tree: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Euen ſo is he ſecluded from the benefite of all good mens prayers, and from the merites of Chriſtes paſſion.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:13014:34"/>
               <p>And here vve may call to mynde à nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble puniſhement of ſuche as after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concilement haue fallen from God in to their former ſinfull practizes. There vvas a company of certein youg men, vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che at the time of eaſter repared to the churche, craued the benefit of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of pennance, vvere abſolued and receiued the bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt his bodie and bloudde. But they vvere no ſoner departed from that holie place, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they dyd fall again to their olde vvicked Ryot, dronkinnes and filthy lyfe. VVhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupon they were greuouſlie puniſhed by the Iuſt Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God. For they were ſodeinlie ſmitten vvith a greuous diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe: and driuen in to ſuche an extreme vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, as they dyd caſt out of their mou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes great abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of corrupt bloudde, vvith their ovvn excreme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes verie lothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomelie, contrarie to the courſe of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Their corne and other fruites vvere conſumed vpon the grounde and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troyed, ſom vvith vvater, and ſome vvith fier. Serpentes and venomous beaſtes dyd breed abundantly in their groundes, in ſuche ſort as theyr perſones were in great daungier. And thus brought in miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:13014:34"/>diſtreſſe many lamented theyr caſe: Emong vvhome one deuout holie man vpon compaſſion prayed to God ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtlie for them, till at laſt an Angell of God appearing to him dyd demaund of him vvhat puniſhement he deſerued that dyd put in to a filthie preſone the Innocent ſonne of a mightie Emperour: the good man anſvvered that he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued greuous puniſhement. Yea (ſayd the Angel) but vvhat puniſhement deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth he vvhiche in the ſight of all men doeth caſt the bleſſed bodye and blood of Chriſt in to a filthy myre? he is to be brent as an heretique, ſayd the good man. And euen ſuche felovves are all they (ſayd the Angel) for vvhom thou haſt ſo long prayde. Therfore it is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for euery good Chriſtian, vvhen he hath receiued the bleſſed Sacrament, and is reconciled to God: then and euer after to take good heed of relapſe: and often to calle to memorye theſe ſeuen miſeries and inconueniences of relapſe here mencioned.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:13014:35"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a deathbed scene, featuring a figure in a bed receiving a blessing from a robed male figure; a second robed male figure and a female figure stand nearby, while two other male figures kneel in prayer</figDesc>
               </figure> Certein ſignes and tokens Thereby a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian after he hath receiued the bleſſed ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament may probablie coniecture that he is in the fauour of God: all framed to the ſimilitude of a ſyk man.</head>
            <p>THe firſt ſigne and token of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour is compunction or harti ſorow for ſinne committed. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For as the ſicke man ſo long as he yeeldeth breth, be he neuer ſo ſick geueth good hope of lyfe: euen ſo a Chriſtian after he haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our Redempoion, if he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiue or caſt ovvt ſorocofull ſighes
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:13014:35"/>for his ſinnes by paſt, in reſpect that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he had offended god, may vvell hope that the bleſſed ſacrament doeth vvoork in him many good ſpirituall effectes, for (as Seynt Barnard ſayeth) the more ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a man hath of ſinne, the greater ſob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes and ſighes he caſteth out of his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rovvfull harte.</p>
            <p>The ſecounde ſigne or token is lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conuerſacion of lyfe vvith good ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> For as a freſhe naturall colour in a ſikman is good argument of amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: ſo is modeſty and temperance a ſpeciall ſigne of Gods grace. And good example is ſo neceſſarie that Seynt Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie ſayeth, ſinnefull men could neuer return to true repentance, if good exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of lyfe vvere taken avvaye. And bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is the ſoule of that perſone (ſayth Seynt Chriſoſtom) vvhoſe humilitie doeth confounde the pryde of an other. For (as Seynt Leo ſayeth) ſo many as thou ſhalt vvinne by example of humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and charitie: vvith them ſhalt thou poſſeſſe eternall revvarde in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendacion of good exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple I haue redde of a good Abbot whiche hearing that there vvas, not farre of his Abbey, a
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:13014:36"/>notable great theefe and robber vvhiche ſpoyled and mordered many paſſing by the common vvayes, had great compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this theefe for his ſinfull lyfe, and ſtudied hovv he might reclame hym. At laſt he thought the beſt vvay to be, firſt to talke vvith him. And though he knevv no mean to doe it vvithout per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall danger to him ſelfe: yet he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to geue a proofe: And taking a Monk in company vvith hym aduentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to paſſe through the place vvhere the theefe haunted. It ſo fell ovvt, that the theefe met the Abbot, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his profeſſion, ſpoyled the Abbot and his companion of all that they had. After a vvhile the theefe hauing gotten his pray, vvaxed ſomevvhat more colde than before: for the Abbot vſed him ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe vvith all humilite in vvorde and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance tovvardes him. And the Abbot perceiuyng the rage of the theefe to be aſſuaged vſed the matter ſo as they tvvo fell in to familiar talke of common mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: As of the great paynes that the theefe indured and of his continuall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill: and of the commodities of ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ſuche like. At laſt the Abbot aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:13014:36"/>him if he could be content to leaue that paynfull, daungerous, and diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red courſe of lyfe for a filthie and vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein gayn: And to goe home vvith the Abbat, vvhere he ſhould be aſſured of a ſufficient liuing vvith great credit and honeſty. After ſome diſcourſe vpon the Abbots vvoord the theefe yeeldeth, and home he cometh vvith the Abbat to the Abbey, vvhere he ſyndeth all thinges that the Abbot had promiſed and more. Novv this good Abbot hoping by good example to vvinne the theefe, appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted one of his monkes a deuout man to attend vpon the theefe, and to geue vvhat ſo euer he demaunded, vvith this admonicion to eat and drink euer in his company, and vvhat deinty meat ſo euer vvas ſet before the theefe, yet he him ſelfe ſhould eat none of it: but content him ſelfe onlie vvith bread and vvater. The monke vvell performed vvhat vvas commaunded. In continuance of time the theefe obſerued vvell the diet of the Monke: and being ſomevvhat amaſed there vvith all, aſked the monke, vvhat great offence he had committed, that cauſed ſuch ſtraitnes of diet, vvhether
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:13014:37"/>he had committed any morder, inceſt, or great crime. No ſayd the Monke, I am not culpable of any haynouſe fact. But this auſteritie I vſe to the ende that the king of all kynges may be more merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to me at the latter day, vvhen euerie mans dedes ſhall appear. This anſvver ſtrooke the theefe vvith ſuche remorſe and repentance, as he came to the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot, and vvith great thankes ſo hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him ſelfe, as he vvas admitted vnto that ſocietie: and became ſo penitent, and after ſo religious, as in holynes and perfection of lyfe he excelled all the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent. Thus may vve ſee vvhat good fruit vertuous examples may bring forthe.</p>
            <p> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third ſigne is patience in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. For as the greefe of ſiknes is eſtemed more or leſſe by the mouynng or reſt of the ſicke mans pulſe: ſo is our perfection and imperfection tried by toleracion of aduerſitie. And as an empty veſſel if you beat vpon it vvill yeeld an Eccho or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lovv ſounde: but, if it be full, no noyſe at all is heard from vvith in the veſſel: So is a patient man tried from a vnpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient man by aduerſitie. The one if he be touched vvith affliction exclameth
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:13014:37"/>againſt God and man: but thother is quyet, taketh all in good part vvhat ſo euer hapneth.</p>
            <p>The fouerth ſigne is the ſenſe of taſt. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> for ſo long as a ſikman eateth his meat vvith a good taſt, it is lyke he vvill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer his healthe; euen ſo if a man haue a delectacion to hear ſpeake or thinke of the paſſion of our Sauiour: of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed lyfe of our lady, and of holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs and Confeſſors, or to be fedd vvith any ſpirituall foode: theſe thinges doe argue ſound health of the ſoule, and a good ſtate of ſpirituall grace in any ſuche perſone, for there can be no more accorde betvvene ſpirituall and vvorld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie pleaſures than betvvene fyre and vvater. Therfore it is impoſſible (ſayth Seynt Ambroſe) in this lyfe to liue deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vvith all vvorldlie pleaſures, and to enioye the pleaſures prepared for the ſoule.</p>
            <p>The fift ſigne is our tongue, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> for it is a good ſigne of a mendement in a ſickeman, vvhen his tongue faultereth not in his mouth, and he ottereth his ſpeech eaſilie and playnlie. Euen ſo it is a right good ſigne of a ſpirituall grace,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:13014:38"/>vvhen a man deliteth in godly talke, and conference of godly matters, vvithout detracting or bakbiting his neighbor, euer interpreting the deedes and vvoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of other men in the beſt ſenſe. For often the tongue vvalketh after the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. And of abundance of the hart, the mouth vſeth to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>The ſixt ſigne is a diſpoſicion to doe good vvoorkes, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> and to be in exerciſe of pietie, for a ſik man, vvhen he begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to recouer deſireth to ſturre and exerciſe his bodye: ſo he that hath a right feeling of the ſpirit of God is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Idle: but euer occupied in good vvoorkes. Other occupacion (vvhat ſo euer it be) is an Idlenes and not an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor exerciſe. Therfore all good vvriters exhort men to be euer occupied in ſome vertuouſe exerciſe.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth ſigne is naturall heat: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> a ſpeciall argument of lyfe in a ſyk bodye. So is the ſpirituall heat of loue of God and our neighbour a ſure ſigne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in a Chriſtian. For (as ſaynt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin ſayeth) loue is the lyfe of the ſoule: In ſo mucheas he vvhiche loueth not, is dead.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:13014:38"/>
               <head>Of certein good documentes touching euell thougtes.</head>
               <p>TOuching euell thoughtes vve haue to conſider for our better inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuerſe ſpeciall matters.</p>
               <p>Firſt the cauſe vvhereof they ariſe. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Secondlie the reaſon vve are ſo prone and inelined to them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Therdlie the hurt that vve receuie by them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Fouertlie hovv vve may arme our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues againſt them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
               </p>
               <p>Fiftlye by vvhat meanes vve may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd them. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 
               </p>
               <p> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As to the firſt it is vvel knovvn that euell thoughtes had their firſt origin and beginning of our profeſſed enem ye the deuill: vvho firſt ſeduced our common mother Eue by his ſuggeſtion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue a vviked thought and there vpon to eate the aple: vvhiche moued delite and lyking: then folovved the conſent of Adam, and conſequentlie the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure and indignacion of allmighty God.</p>
               <p>Touching the ſecond poynt: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> among many there are three ſpeciall cauſes of</p>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:13014:39"/>
               <head>Certein godlie leſſons and obſeruacions touching the hart of man.</head>
               <p>GOD requyreth the hart of man, and to haue the poſſeſſion of yt. And three reaſons may begeuen to moue hym therunto. One is, for that the hart is as it vvere the harbarovv of the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, and the proper bedchamber or cabinet of the king. Again the hart is the principall ſeate and firſt member that receyueth lyfe. And by naturall conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence the hart being full of bloudde is apter to conceiue an impreſſion of hym that ſhedde is bloude for vs vpon the croſſe.</p>
               <p>God deſireth a purified hart. And thre thinges there are vvhiche purifie the hart. The firſt is a carefull examinacion daily of our ovvn vvoordes, deades and thoughtes, vvith a ſpeciall deſire to geue good example to others. The ſecond is, daily pennance vvith due confeſſion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition and ſatisfaction for our offenſes againſt God and our neigbour. The third is continuall crauing and begging of God by deuout prayer to be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by his Grace from all occaſions and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:13014:39"/>matters that may offend God. for (as the prophet Dauid ſayeth) <hi>If our lorde haue not buylded the houſe; in vain haue they labored whiche buylded it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A pure and clean hart is knovvne by three ſignes or markes. The firſt is the quicke and pregnant knouleige of our ovvne defectes. For as a ſmall ſpot is ſone eſpied in a verie vvhite linnen clothe: ſo a pure hart quickelie perceiueth a ſmall fault in it ſelfe. The ſecond is quietnes of conſcience in all troubles and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. For a pure good vvine in a cleane glaſſe changeth not his colour and clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be it neuer ſo muche troubled: euen ſo a pure hart and cleane conſcience is vvell ſetled and reſteth euer in one eſtate vvhat aduerſitie ſo euer hapneth. The third mark is encreaſe of couraige in time of affliction euen as a pure freſh vvine ſprinkleth and leapeth vvhen it is vvith any force poured in to a Cuppe.</p>
               <p>And our hart is preſerued in puritie and cleanneſſe by a true fear of God: by a carefull gouernement of our externall ſenſes, and by continuall exerciſe of the vvoorkes of charitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:13014:40"/>
               <head>Fouer good leſſons for preſeruing our hope and confidence in God.</head>
               <p>NOvv to make an end: vve muſt euer ſtudie to eſtabliſh our affiance and truſt in God againſt all tentacions: And one ſpeciall good mean therunto is a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient and quiet mynd, neyther too negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and recheles, nor too anxious and carefull about our temporall affayrs. As for example, touching our bodily ſuſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion and neceſſities vve muſt not be ouer ſolicitous: but reſt vpon this groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, that ſithe it is true that the geuer of all good thinges doeth nouriſh the byrdes of the eyr, fiſhes in the ſea, and beaſtes on the earth euerie one in his degree and qualitie, to vvhom yet he hathe made no promis therof: hovv muche more cauſe haue vve to hope that he vvill prouide for vs, to vvhome his promys is paſt? as appeareth in the ſixt of Seynt Mathevv, vvhere he deliuereth vs of all ſuche care, an ſayth in expreſſe vvoordes. <hi>Be not care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſayeing, what ſhall we eat, or what ſhall we drinke, or were with ſhall we be couered? Seek first the kingdome of God: and all theſe thinges ſhalbe geuen you beſides.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:13014:40"/>
               <p>And too muche care for other tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall thinges is forbidden as a very daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous tentacion. As vvell for that in this vvorlde vve are but as pilgrimes or vvay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayring men, hauing here no place of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein abyding, but are to remoue vpon many ſuddain occaſions; and to clogge and ouer lode our ſelues vvith ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties vver mere ſolye: As all ſo and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for that ſuche carefullnes is ſeldome or neuer vvithout ſinne, and vvithdra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vveth our myndes from prouiding for thinges of mere neceſſite and of great importance touching our ſoule: And it argueth in vs a greater loue and affection tovvardes thies vanities, than tovvardes the vvealth of our ſoul. Agayn vvhere they are not got vvithout great labour, nor kept vvithout care, they are quickie loſt and notvvithout great greefe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this carefullnes and loue to vvorld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye thinges is to be eſchevved. For (as S. Gregorie ſayeth,) <hi>That whiche is poſſeſſed without great loue or affection therto, ye alſo lost without any great greefe.</hi> Let vs then forſake the care of tranſitorie thinges, and ſetle our truſt in God, vvho neuer failed thoſe that put their affiance in him. Examples vve haue infinite to proue the ſame.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:13014:41"/>
               <p>An other preſeruatiue is a mature and rype diſcrecion and Iudgement in vvei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghing and conſidering our ſinnes. For many curiouſe ſimple men, as vvell as the ſinfull and vvicked vpon repentance looke ſo farre in to theyr lyfe only as they forget the mercie of God, and fall into deſpare and blaſphemye. It is ther fore good and verie neceſſarie euer with all conſideracions of our ſinnes, to call to mynde the article of our faith, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching remiſſion of ſinnes, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God for the ſame: vvherof holy ſcripture hath great plentie. As vvhere the Prophet ſayeth: In vvhat hovvre a ſinner is ſory and confeſſeth his ſinnes they are all put out of mynde: God is bothe hable and vvilling to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue a penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſinner be his ſinnes neuer ſo great. But no man can haue true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, nor doe right pennance vvhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che doeth it not vvith a firm hope of forgeuenes, and vvithout all miſtruſt and diffidence of the promis of God. Accuſed ther fore at the deſperat before our Sauiour vvhiche ſayeth, I vvil not the death of a ſinner, but rather that he be conuerted and liue.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:13014:41"/>
               <p>Another good aſſurance vve haue to confirme our hope in god: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and that is his faithfull promis that he is vvillinge and reddie, graciouſlie to hear vs in all our petitions vvhiche are for our good. For our Sauiour ſayeth:
<note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Aſke and it ſhabbe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you: ſeeke and you ſhal finde: knocke and it ſhall be opened to you, for euerie one that aſketh, receiueth, &amp;c. And we know that he heareth vs (ſaith Seynt Iohn) what ſoeuer we ſhall aſke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to his will. Alwayes prouided that we aſke in fayth nothing doubting.</hi> as Seynt Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes byddeth vs: For the aſker of lavv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full thinges may not either miſtruſt gods povver and habilitie, or be in deſpair of his mercie: but that the doubte vve haue be onely in our ovvne vnvvoorthineſſe or vndue aſking.</p>
               <p>A fouerth good ſtaye vve haue to lean vpon, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> and to preſerue our hope and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence. And that is the faithfull promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of eternall lyfe geuen vs by God, if vve liue here according to his vvill and commaundement doeing pennance for our ſinnes, and leaning to his mercye in faith hope and Charitie: for God is moſt faithfull and euer keepeth his promiſſe vvith all men. Therfore if vve vvil not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:13014:42"/>be lyke to the vvaues of the fea vvhiche are caried about vvith the vvinde: let vs flee from too muche care of tranſitorie thinges, and keep in our minde and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie the promiſe of God euer offering his grace to vs, reddie to hear and help vs. So ſhall vve preſerue the hoope and confidence that God requireth of vs: to vvhom be all honor and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>A prayer to our bleſſed lady made by the moſt holy and auncient Ephrem.</head>
            <p>MOther of God vndefiled, Queen of al, the hope of them that deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, my lady moſt glorious, higher than the heuenly ſpirites, more honorable than the Cherubines, holier than the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphines, and vvithout compariſon mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re glorious than the ſupernall hoſtes, the hoope of the fathers, the glorie of the Prophets, the praiſe of the Apoſtles, by thee vve are reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled to Chriſt my God, thy ſonne: thou art the helper of ſinners: the hauen for them that are toſſed vvith
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:13014:42"/>ſtormes, the ſolace of the redempcion of captiues: voucheſafe me thy ſeruant to praiſe thee. Haile Lady Marie full of grace: Haile Virgin moſt bleſſed among vvomen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>An other prayer made by Seynt Cirill.</head>
            <p>PRaiſe and glorie be to thee o holie Trinitie: to thee alſo be praiſe, o ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mother of God, for thou art the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pearle of the vvorlde: thou art the ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>del of vnguenſheble light, the croune of virginitie, the ſcepter of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique faithe. By thee the Trinitie is glorifyed and adored in all the vvorlde: by thee heauen reioyceth, Angels and Archangels are glad, diuels are put to flyght, and man is called again to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and euery creature that vvas held vvith the errors of Idols is turned to the knovvleidge of truthe: by thee Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are founded through the vvorlde: thou being their helper, the Gentiles come to pennance. O bleſſed Marie, vvho can be hable vvor thelie to praiſe or thanke thee: receiue our prayers, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanie our requeſtes: for thou art the ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall hoope of ſinners, by thee vve hoope
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:13014:43"/>for perdone of our ſynnes: and in thee (o moſt bleſſed) is the expectacion of our revvardes.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>An admonicion for the vnlearned touching the vſe of the figure of the beades here after portrued.</head>
            <p>THou haſt here (gentle reder) a figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re or forme of the beades; vvith cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein matters of meditacion to be vſed vvhen thou art diſpoſed to recite the crovvne of our ladie vpon the beades vvhiche matters haue not bene before this tyme put into engliſhe meter, for the beter memorie and delectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout perſons. Therfore if thou haſt bene here to fore delited vvith vain ballads and ſonets, thou may novv vpon better aduiſe pleaſe thy ſelfe vvith ſonges and ditties more profitable. And of vvhat good trade, occupacion or qualiue ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you are, vvhiles you goe about your neceſſarie buſineſſe in your vocation, or vvhiles you are traualing by the vvaye: or in tillinge or plovvinge the grovvnd that hit may bring great increaſe, you may not vvithſtanding, ſome tyme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:13014:43"/>call vpon our Sauiour or vpon the bleſſed virgin mary, eyther in vvorde or in thought, and vvith great comfort, yea and profit alſo both ſpirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, repeat or thinke vpon the Pater noſter and Aue Mary, or ſome part ther of, and of the verſes, or of ſome of them ſet dovvne in the table folovvinge. And ther vpon may you take occaſion to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe and thinke leſſe or more of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters conteyned in the verſes or any of them. VVher vpon you by Gods grace ſhall be induced in to a ſvvete cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion vvhat ſpeciall graces God hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtovved vpon you; from vvhat euells he hath preſerued you; to vvhat good ende he hath created you: vvhat good reward he hath prouided for you, yf you come to that end: and to come vnto it you are aſſured if you be ſo vvilling as you ought to be. Thus ſhall you alſo take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to kepe your ſelf vvell occupied, auoyde idle thoughts, the ſnares of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and ſo kepe your ſelf in the vvay tovvardes heauen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:13014:44"/>
            <p>WHer as I haue ſeen your Ladi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip accept, ſuch holy and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teus exerciſes, and holde them in great eſtimacion, and conſter all faul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes eſcaped by the print to verteus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretacion: taking the meaning, and not the letter; ſo I hoope your holy vſe vvil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be a meane, that I ſhall not be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geither diſliked of ſuch vvhos handes hit cometh vnto: But as I aſhure my ſelfe, all baniſhed parſons liuing for one cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe, vvil not diſpiſe good thoughtes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedinge of holy deſiers, and eſpecially thos, vvhos vviſdoms knovv hovv hard it is to print our languaig, in a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie vvith out faultes: vvich maketh me ſo farre preſume apon all holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke perſons, eſpecially ſuch of honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble conſideracion, and haue ſo long ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued à baniſhed lief for true religions ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke: as your honor hath donne this 17 Yeres. In this conſideracion, I preſume of all good Catholickes, that they vvill eſteme of my meaning, and not the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: as I ſhall not ceaſe dayly and orderly to praye for all eſtates, truſting in IESV, he vvill hear a poor pilgrome and baniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed parſon: for his righteouſnes ſake:
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:13014:44"/>that hit ſhal pleaſe him to conuert our poor countery, vvher vve maye praye togeither, liue togeither, and die togei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the end vve maye be partakers of his heauenly kingdoome, vvher God the father, God the ſonne, God the holy ghoſt, is glorefied: vvher the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en is crouned, vvher Angels, Saints, and marters reioys, at our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; for wich I daily praye to be geuen to all ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners ſayinge.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Pater noster, Aue Maria.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>CREDO</q>
            <closer>
               <signed>Good reder remember me in the like. I. B.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>depiction of the virgin Mary</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:13014:45"/>
            <p>Hic liber nihil mali aut erronei continet: conducit autem ad deuotionem &amp; pietatem im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritiorum Anglorum.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GILBERTVS BVRNEFORDVS. GVLIELMVS CLIDERO. Angli Sacerdotes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Horum duorum eruditorum &amp; fide digno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum virorum iudicio &amp; ego ſubſcribo</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. CVYCKIVS <hi>Apostolicus &amp; Regius libro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum cenſor.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:13014:45"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
